Guide to the Washington Office on Latin America Records, 1962-2020 and undated, bulk 1974-2005; 1962-ongoing RL.01401
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Geographic Series, 1962-2008 and undated, 250 boxes
  - Argentina, 1976-2004 and undated, 5 boxes
    Clippings, correspondence, and files primarily concerned with Argentina's stance towards political expression and human rights. Most material is dated between the late 1970s and the early 1980s. Prominent topics include cases of extrajudicial imprisonment of dissidents by the government, several of which were brought before the Interamerican Commission on Human Rights (IACHR). In addition, some files document controversies over proposed sales of arms to Argentina by the United States and Argentina's support of conservative authoritarian regimes in El Salvador and Bolivia. Material was created by WOLA staff, including Rachel Nield and Coletta Youngers.
    Separated Materials note
    [Some items removed to Oversize Material.]
    - Argentina files (Box 44-48)
  - Bolivia, 1989-1998 and undated, 2 boxes
    Files and clippings on the Bolivian state and economy, almost all of which concern drug policy in some way. Many of these document U.S. relations with Bolivia, particularly with respect to military aid to combat drug processing and trafficking. Some documents and reports also examine Bolivian economic development in the context of creating economically viable alternatives for coca farmers. Finally, human rights abuses, most at the hands of foreign-controlled drug cartels, are documented. Additional Bolivia-related material may be found in the Drug Policy Subseries of the Initiatives and Activities Series.
    - Bolivia files (Box 49-50)
  - Brazil, 1986, 2002-2005, 3.5 boxes
    Files documenting WOLA's programs in Brazil. Much of the material relates to Brazilian elections, particularly that of Luiz Inácio Lula da Silva, and possible alliances between politically left regimes in Latin America. Clippings and other material related to Brazilian agriculture are also included.
    - Brazil files (Box 51-54)
  - Chile, 1969-2004 and undated, 18 boxes
    Divided into files and materials collected by Patrick Ahern and those created by WOLA. The majority of the material in this subseries chronicles the events surrounding the 1973 coup that installed General Augusto Pinochet as leader of Chile and the ramifications of this event over several decades. The Patrick Ahern Files consist of material collected by Ahern, a Catholic priest with an interest in liberation theology. The bulk of this grouping consists of printed material from a range of Chilean and internationally based sources, many of which predate or run concurrently with the coup. Material in the subject files subgrouping documents the immediate aftermath of the coup and the response of key actors in the United States. WOLA Files contain clippings, press releases, correspondence, and reports on human rights abuses and the Chilean political environment. These focus on U.S. relations with Chile including the bombing of exiled diplomat Orlando Letelier in Washington D.C. and the changing political climate in Chile in the late 1980s and early 1990s. Finally, files from the 2000s chronicle international attempts to bring Pinochet to trial for human rights abuses and the Chilean state's response to these efforts.
    - Patrick Ahern Files, 1969-1983, 8 boxes
      The bulk of this grouping consists of Printed Material, including newspaper and magazine clippings, comic books, pamphlets, scholarly papers, monographs, and serials. In addition, a Subject Files subgrouping mainly comprises materials related to events following the 1973 coup and the response of key actors in the United States, including the nascent NGO community (including the first iteration of WOLA), members of the U.S. Congress, and various church organizations. The Ahern files contain some ephemera relating to Fidel Castro, assassinated president Salvador Allende's political campaign, and U.S.-based movements supporting Chileans persecuted under the Pinochet regime.
      - Printed Material, 1971-1983 and undated
        A collection of valuable early and sometimes ephemeral printed material on social and political conditions in Chile organized into the following subgroups: Clippings, Comics, Other Printed Material, and Serials. Clippings are from Chile- and U.S.-based publications. Most of the Chilean clippings are from El Mercurio, Chile's largest newspaper which is alleged to have undermined the Allende government with its editorial stance. Other titles represented include La Nacion, La Prensa, 3ra De La Hora. English language clippings come from the New York Times, Wall Street Journal, and Washington Post, as well as the Washington D.C.-based Daily Rag, The Eagle (student newspaper of American University), the Fond Du Lac Reporter (Wisconsin), and the Rocky Mountain News (Denver, CO). A collection of Spanish language Comics are represented in the collection. With the exception of copies of Archi and El Condorito, all are leftist and explicitly political. These include La Firme and La Firme Extra, Documentos Especiale, and a comic book explaining how to vote. Pamphlets, conference materials, scholarly articles, and monographs are grouped in Other Printed Material. Serials in the Patrick Ahern Files date from the period leading up to the 1973 coup through the late 1970s. These include a mostly complete run of Chile Hoy (1971-1973) and Mensaje (1971-1976), and numerous issues of Ercilla and Solidaridad.
        - Clippings
          - 1972-1976, 5 folders (Box 54)
          - American publications, 1973-1974 (Box 54)
          - Advertisements and headlines, 1971-1972 (Box 54)
          - Spanish language publications, 1973-1974 (Box 54)
        - Comics
          - Archi, El Condorito, 1972 Oct., undated (Box 54)
          - Documentos Especiales, undated (Box 54)
          - La Firme, undated (Box 54)
          - La Firme Extra, undated (Box 54)
          - ¡Vamos Leyendo!, undated (Box 54)
          - "Votando en Marzo", undated (Box 54)
        - Other Printed Material (Box 54-57)
        - Serials
          - Chile Newsletter, 1974-1976 (Box 57)
          - Community Action on Latin America, 1972-1973 (Box 57)
          - Ercilla, 1971-1974, 5 folders (Box 57)
          - Hora Cero, 1972-1973, 2 folders (Box 58)
          - Mensaje, 1971-1975, 1-7 of 8 folders (Box 58)
          - Mensaje, 1972-1976, 8 of 8 folders (Box 59)
          - MIR [Movimiento de la Izquierda Revolucionaria] Resistance Courier and other publications, 1974-1976, 2 folders (Box 59)
          - NACLA Latin America and Empire Report, 1973-1978, 2 folders (Box 59)
          - Pastoral Popular, 1971-1973, 2 folders (Box 59)
          - Que Pasa, 1973, 2 folders (Box 59)
          - Revista de la Universidad Tecnica del Estado, 1972-1973, 1-2 of 3 folders (Box 59)
          - Revista de la Universidad Tecnica del Estado, 1972-1973, 3 of 3 folders (Box 60)
          - Unsorted serials, 1971-1978, 6 folders (Box 60)
      - Subject Files, 1971-1976 and undated
        Contain files primarily related to solidarity movements organized against the Pinochet regime in the 1970s and early 1980s. Events and files in this section include those related to the 1976 assassination of Orlando Letelier, Chilean Ambassador to the United States under Allende in Washington D.C., files from several conferences organized in response to the 1973 coup and allegations of U.S. involvement in it, and the plight of individuals imprisoned by the military junta for political reasons. Also contains some ephemera relating to Fidel Castro, Allende's political campaign, and U.S.-based movements supporting Chileans persecuted under the Pinochet regime.
        - Chile political repression files from U.S. sources, 1974 (Box 60)
        - Chile-recent, 1974-1976, undated, 2 folders (Box 60)
        - Chile-right, 1975-1976, undated (Box 61)
        - Church-related, 1975, undated (Box 61)
        - Ephemera undated (Box 61)
        - Ephemera and clippings, 1972-1973, undated (Box 61)
        - Handbills and ephemera, 1971, undated (Box 61)
        - Latin American files and clippings, 1973, undated (Box 61)
        - Letelier/Moffitt car bombing files, 1976 (Box 61)
        - U.S.-Chile, Letelier assassination files and clippings, 1974-1976, undated (Box 61)
        - U.S.-Chile policy critique files, 1974, undated (Box 61)
        - Washington D.C. Chile coalition, 1975, undated (Box 61)
        - Washington Office on Latin America communiques, 1975, undated (Box 61)
    - WOLA Files, 1978-2004, 9.5 boxes (Box 62-71)
      The WOLA Files on Chile consist of clippings, press releases, and correspondence, chiefly related to the 1989 democratic elections in Chile, the first in that country since the 1973 coup. Several files concern the assassination of Orlando Letelier and his assistant Ronnie Moffitt and international efforts to bring their killers to justice. In addition some files document human rights abuses of the junta helmed by Pinochet, among these a three-volume copy of the report issued by the Chilean Truth and Reconciliation Commission. Efforts of human rights groups and some in the international community to bring Pinochet to trial in the late 1990s and early 2000s are documented as well.
  - Colombia, 1982-2008 and undated, 25 boxes
    Organized in the following folder groups: Human Rights; Politics and Government; Printed Material; U.S. Relations; and WOLA Files. United States drug control policy (commonly called the War on Drugs) forms the backdrop against which nearly all files are set. Files chronicle the Colombian government's attempts to maintain control within its borders against drug cartels and guerilla and paramilitary groups. The United States' role in Colombia, both as a military advisor and as a critic of alleged human rights abuses by the military are documented. Human Rights files examine specific cases of rights violations as well as more general reports by Colombian and U.S.-based organizations. Material in the Politics and Government grouping cover domestic issues in Colombia, including elections, the administration of justice, and the faltering peace process between the state and the Fuerzas Armadas Revolucionarias de Colombia–Ejército del Pueblo (FARC-EP or FARC) the largest guerilla faction in Colombia. Printed Material consists of reports and serials. Most are published by U.S.-based institutions (including WOLA), although some by Colombian government agencies and human rights groups appear as well. Files on U.S. Relations with Colombia include testimony before Congress; correspondence by members of Congress to other leaders in the U.S. and Colombia; and numerous debates about foreign aid to Colombia to combat drug cultivation and distribution. WOLA's efforts to shape the policy debate in the United States are documented in WOLA Files, the largest grouping. Correspondence with officials in the U.S. and Colombia, reports and information relevant to pending legislation (known to WOLA staff as "Hill drops"), material related to conferences and programs organized by WOLA, and files coordinating delegations to Colombia make up the bulk of these files. One compact disc entitled Rehenes de las FARC and one videocassette complete the subseries. Material created by WOLA staff, including Charles Call, Jason Hagen, Tina Hodges, Winifred Tate, and Coletta Youngers, whose names can often be found in materials or on file folders. Additional files related to Colombia may be found in the Drug Policy Subseries of the Initiatives and Activities Series.
    - Human Rights, 1988-2003 and undated (Box 71-74)
    - Politics and Government, 1982-1999 and undated (Box 74-77)
    - Printed Material, 1993-2008 and undated
      - American Friends Service Committee, 1999 (Box 77)
      - Campaña Nacional e Internacional por los Derechos de los Pueblos, undated (Box 77)
      - Cien Dias, 1990-1998, 3 folders (Box 77)
      - CINEP [Centro de Investigación y Educación Popular], 1991 (Box 77)
      - Colombia Internacional, 1994-1996 (Box 77)
      - Colombian state publications, 1998-2002, undated, 1 of 3 folders (Box 77)
      - Colombian state publications, 1998-2002, undated, 2-3 of 3 folders (Box 78)
      - CREDHOS, Situación Regional D.H. y D.I.H., 2001-2002 (Box 78)
      - Comite Permanente por la Defensa de los Derechos Humanos, 2001-2003, 2 folders (Box 78)
      - Controversia, 1998-1999 (Box 78)
      - Defensoría del Pueblo, 2002, 2 folders (Box 78)
      - Desde la Region, 2002 (Box 78)
      - Diócesis de Quibdó publications, 2002, undated (Box 78)
      - Institute for National Strategic Studies [INSS] Strategic Forum, 1997-1998 (Box 78)
      - International Crisis Group, 2002 (Box 78)
      - Non-Governmental Liaison Service [NGLS] development dossiers, 1995-1996 (Box 79)
      - NGLS, Go Between, 1995-1997 (Box 79)
      - NGLS, Round Up, 1995-1997 (Box 79)
      - Nova + Vetera, 2001-2002 (Box 79)
      - Oficena en Colombia del Alto Comisionado de las U.N. para los D.H., 2002 (Box 79)
      - Organización Feminina Popular, 2002, undated (Box 79)
      - Pax Christi kidnapping reports, 2001 (Box 79)
      - Political info kits, 2002 (Box 79)
      - Redepaz, 1999, undated (Box 79)
      - Resguardo Indigena Inga de Aponte, 2001 (Box 79)
      - Strategic Studies Institute publications, 2001-2002 (Box 79)
      - Trans Fugas, 1998-1999 (Box 79)
      - Transnational Institute Briefing Papers, 2001, 2002 (Box 79)
      - UN Documents, 1998, 2002, undated (Box 80)
      - UN development program, 1999, 2002, undated (Box 80)
      - UNESCO [United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization] News, 1994-1995 (Box 80)
      - University of Miami North-South Center publications, 2001-2002, 2 folders (Box 80)
      - Utopias, 1996-1999, undated, 5 folders (Box 80)
      - WOLA publications, 1993-2008, 5 folders (Box 81)
      - Woodrow Wilson International Center publications, 1996, 2000-2002, 2 folders (Box 81)
      - World Bank publications, 1995, 1998-1999, 2 folders (Box 81)
      - Unsorted printed material, 1-3 of 14 folders (Box 81)
      - Unsorted printed material, 4-11 of 14 folders (Box 82)
      - Unsorted printed material, 12-14 of 14 folders (Box 83)
    - U.S. Relations, 1991-2002 and undated (Box 83-86)
    - WOLA Files, 1989-2003 and undated (Box 86-96)
      Conditions Governing Access note
      [Original audiovisual material closed to use. Technical Services may need to have a use copy made before contents can be accessed. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.]
  - Costa Rica, 1984-1993 and undated, 2 boxes
    Files on Costa Rican economy and politics, many relating explicitly to the Contra War. Covers the 1986 election of Óscar Arias Sánchez and Costa Rica's ongoing issues with debt service related to development aid. Relations with the U.S. figure prominently in this subseries, with respect to economic and military aid and Costa Rica's efforts to remain a neutral party in the Nicaraguan conflict. Also contains some material describing the state of human rights in Costa Rica, particularly relating to the counter-revolutionary forces (often called "Contras") that used Costa Rica's northern border as a staging area for incursions into Nicaragua. While nearly all files explicitly refer to Costa Rica, a few relate to the larger surrounding region and the Contra War more generally. Researchers interested in the Nicaraguan conflict should consult subseries on Nicaragua and Honduras as well.
    - Costa Rica files (Box 97-98)
  - Cuba, 1962, 1994-2006 and undated, 10 boxes
    Pertains chiefly to the U.S. trade embargo with Cuba. Organized into the following folder groups: Human Rights, Other Material, and U.S. Relations. Human Rights is the smallest group in the subseries and contains files and reports related to Cuban human rights concerns, particularly the topics of political dissidents and religious freedom. A number of general reports from human rights organizations are included as well. Other Material consists of general files related to Cuban political history; files associated with conferences and seminars, the bulk organized by WOLA; documents on Cuba's relationship with the (non-U.S.) international community; and files related to the status of churches in Cuba, particularly the 1998 visit by the Pope.
    The bulk of the subseries is housed in the U.S. Relations grouping. Most of this material relates to details of the longstanding U.S.-imposed trade and travel embargo. Files in this group document escalations of the embargo policy, particularly the 1996 Helms-Burton Act (also known as LIBERTAD), as well as calls for its easement or removal by members of Congress, WOLA, and other organizations. Many files concern the removal of restrictions on humanitarian aid to Cuba, travel restrictions to the island for U.S. citizens, and efforts by farm lobbies to open Cuba to U.S. agricultural exports. Additional files document allegations of Cuban links to terrorist activities by U.S. officials after September 11, 2001 as well as arguments against these claims. Finally, copies of a declassified 1962 Defense Department memorandum outlining the possible instigation of armed conflict with Cuba (Box 107) and declassified reports on the trial of anti-Castro fighter Orlando Bosch in Venezuela are included. WOLA staff, particularly Liah Rosenblum and Geoff Thale assembled and maintained material in this subseries.
    - Human Rights, 1995-2003 and undated (Box 99)
    - Other Material, 1994-2004 and undated (Box 99-101)
    - U.S. Relations, 1962, 1994-2006 and undated (Box 101-108)
  - Ecuador, 2002, 3 folders
    One folder containing information on a conference in Ecuador on anti-drug crop fumigation. Issues of the newsletter Ecuador Focus and a file of information on a sign-on letter protesting a break-in at the offices of the Fundación Regional de Asesoría en Derechos Humanos (INREDH) in Quito follow.
    - Ecuador files (Box 108)
  - El Salvador 1986-2004 and undated, 9 boxes
    The bulk of the material on El Salvador focuses on economic and human rights issues raised by the civil war, which lasted for eleven years from 1981-1992, between the government and the leftist political party, the Frente Farabundo Martí para la Liberación Nacional (FMLN). The subseries is separated into Economic Development, Human Rights, and Other Material. The Economic Development subseries includes newsletters, pamphlets, and other writings on development in El Salvador as well as reconstruction after Hurricane Mitch in 1998 and the devastating earthquake of 2001. Documents relating to agrarian reform, land transfers, and outsourcing of U.S. jobs to El Salvador also are found in Economic Development, as are records of international financial aid not contingent on human rights issues. Within Human Rights are records of international aid dependent upon the address of human rights violations (especially by the government's armed forces). Also encompasses clippings, formal reports, correspondence, and documentation of WOLA events revolving around elections, democratization, immigration, labor, judicial reform, criminal codes, and reform of the PNC (La Policía Nacional Civil). The majority of the material pertaining to U.S. foreign policy towards El Salvador appears in Human Rights, and these boxes contain original documents from the truth commission, the United Nations Observer Mission in El Salvador (ONUSAL), the peace accords of 1992, and the FMLN. One VHS cassette produced by the American Jewish World Service appears at the beginning of this grouping. Other Material consists of issues of the Salvadoran magazine Tendencias dated from 1991-1994 as well as copies of El Salvador Proceso. Conference material, files on elections and the solidarity group El Salvador Policy Project complete the subseries. While nearly all files refer exclusively to El Salvador, a few also address Nicaragua-centered Contra War. Material has been arranged as received and only separated insofar as was necessary to generate the categories described above.
    - Economic Development, 1989-2001 and undated (Box 109-111)
    - Human Rights, 1986-2004 and undated (Box 111-118)
      [Original video closed to use. Technical Services staff may need to arrange to have viewing copy made. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.]
    - Other Material, 1991-1994 (Box 118)
  - Guatemala, 1965-2008 and undated, 53 boxes
    Spans the dates 1965-2007 with the bulk of the material dated between 1978 and 2005. Subseries is divided into the following folder groups: Economy and Development; Human Rights; Peace Process; Politics and Government; Printed Material; U.S. Relations; and WOLA Files. Material details the political situation in Guatemala from domestic and international perspectives. Most of the files in this subseries relate to the conflict between guerilla groups and the government that began in 1960 through the 1996 peace accords and the tenuous process of building civil society afterward. The bulk of the material concerns human rights in some way. WOLA personnel who created and maintained material in this subseries include Adriana Beltran, Hugh Byrne, Rachel Garst, Susan Peacock, and Bonnie Tenneriello, whose names sometimes appear in materials or on folders.
    - Economy and Development, 1974-2005 and undated (Box 119-121)
      Consists of reports on the state of the Guatemalan economy and moves towards development, including agrarian land reform, labor conditions, and reports by international donors and organizations. Issues of rural development; agriculture including coffee and genetically modified corn; and government fiscal policy implemented to satisfy the World Bank, Inter-American Development Bank (IDB) and others comprise the majority of the material.
    - Human Rights, 1978-2003 and undated (Box 121-134)
      Case files on instances of human rights violations as well as general reports by various local and international human rights organizations. Most case files document abuses by forces linked to the Guatemalan military, including the rural Patrullas de Autodefensa Civil (PAC), assassinations of clergy and political figures, forced disappearances and torture of prisoners, and the so-called death squads. A considerably smaller number of human rights abuses by guerilla forces may also be found here. Prominent human rights cases include the murder of Guatemalan anthropologist Myrna Mack Chang (in whose memory Fundacion Myrna Mack, a key partner organization of WOLA's was founded), the massacre at Xaman, the rape and torture of Sr. Diana Ortiz, and the assassination of Bishop Juan José Gerardi. Human rights organizations whose reports appear in this grouping, most based outside Guatemala, include Human Rights Watch, Amnesty International and the Guatemalan Human Rights Commission. Because the resolutions to some of these cases became seminal components of the peace process, researchers are strongly encouraged to consult files in the Peace Process grouping for human rights issues.
    - Peace Process, 1982,1988, 1994-2002 and undated (Box 134-146)